I just came back from a community
انا عائدة من مجتمع
that holds the secret to human survival.
يحمل في طياته سر نجاة البشرية
It's a place where women run the show,
انه مكان تديره النساء
have sex to say hello,
ويمارسون الجنس فيه كوسيلة تحية
and play rules the day --
واللعب فيه
where fun is serious business.
والمتعة عنصر اساسي في مجتمعهم
And no, this isn't Burning Man
انه .. ليس مجتمع الآثمين
or San Francisco.
او سان فرنسيسكو
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Ladies and gentlemen, meet your cousins.
سيداتي سادتي .. قابوا أبناء عمومتكم
This is the world of wild bonobos
انه عالم " قردة البابون "
in the jungles of Congo.
في ادغال الكونغو
Bonobos are, together with chimpanzees,
إن " قردة البابون " مع قردة الشمبانزي
your living closest relative.
هم اقرب فصيل لنا على وجه هذا الكوكب
That means we all share a common ancestor,
وهذا يعني اننا نتشارك الأب الواحد ..
an evolutionary grandmother,
أي ان اجدادنا في سلم التطور مشتركون
who lived around six million years ago.
والذين كانوا يعيشون منذ 6 ملاين عام
Now, chimpanzees are well-known
ان فصيل الشمبانزي
for their aggression.
معروف بعدائيته
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But unfortunately,
وللاسف .. قمنا بسحب
we have made too much of an emphasis
هذا الاعتقاد
of this aspect
بصورة مشابهة
in our narratives of human evolution.
على أقربائنا الاقرب لنا " قردة البابون "
But bonobos show us
لقد أرتنا " قردة البابون "
the other side of the coin.
الجانب الآخر من القصة
While chimpanzees
بينما فصيل الشامبنزي
are dominated by big, scary guys,
يتحكم بها قردة ذكور كبيرة مخيفة
bonobo society
فإن مجتمع " قردة البابون "
is run by empowered females.
يترأسه إناثٌ
These guys have really worked something out,
ان هذا الفصيل قد انتج اسلوب حياة
since this leads to a highly tolerant society
فيه الكثير من التسامح
where fatal violence
والعنف فيه
has not been observed yet.
يكاد يكون معدوماً على الاطلاق
But unfortunately,
ولكن لسوء الحظ
bonobos are the least understood
إن فصيل " قردة البابون " هو فصيل لم نفهمه جيداً
of the great apes.
وعممنا ما نعلمه من فصيل القردة الكبيرة عليه
They live in the depths of the Congolese jungle,
انهم يعيشون في عمق ادغال الكنغو
and it has been very difficult to study them.
ومن الصعب جداً القيام باجراء دراسات عليهم
The Congo is a paradox --
ان الكونغو بلد يحوي تناقضاً
a land of extraordinary biodiversity and beauty,
انه بلد فيه الكثير من الروعة والتمايز الطبيعي
but also the heart of darkness itself --
ولكنه بلد الظلم ذاته
the scene of a violent conflict
فالعنف المستشري هناك
that has raged for decades
مستمر منذ عقود
and claimed nearly as many lives
قد حصد ما يقارب ضحايا
as the First World War.
الحرب العالمية الاولى
Not surprisingly,
ولن نتفاجىء
this destruction also endangers bonobo survival.
ان طال قردة البابون حصة من هذا العنف وهو يهدد اليوم بقاءها
Bushmeat trades and forest loss
فصائدي الطرائد .. وفقدان الغابات
means we couldn't fill a small stadium
أدى الى تقلص عدد القردة
with all the bonobos that are left in the world --
بحيث لن نستطيع ان نملاً ملعب كرة قدم بهم
and we're not even sure of that to be honest.
هذا على افضل تقدير
Yet, in this land of violence and chaos,
ورغم ان الكونغو بلد العنف والفوضى
you can hear hidden laughter
الا انه يمكن سماع ضحكات خفية
swaying the trees.
تتجول على اغصان الاشجار
Who are these cousins?
من هم اولاد العمومة هؤلاء ؟
We know them as the "make love, not war" apes
نحن نعرفهم بقردة " ممارسة الحب لا الحرب "
since they have frequent, promiscuous
بسبب انهم يقومون بتصرفات " فاسقة " طيلة الوقت
and bisexual sex
ناهيكم عن الشذوذ
to manage conflict
كحلٍ للنزاعات لديهم
and solve social issues.
وللقضايا الاجتماعية
Now, I'm not saying this is the solution
انا لا أقترح ان هذا هو الحل ..
to all of humanity's problems --
لقضايانا !
since there's more to bonobo life
على اعتبار هناك طرق حل
than the Kama Sutra.
غير " الكاما سورتا "
Bonobos, like humans,
ان قردة البابون .. كما البشر
love to play throughout their entire lives.
تحب اللعب طيلة حياتها
Play is not just child's games.
فاللعب ليس فحسب محصور على الاطفال
For us and them,
سواء لنا كبشر .. او لهم كقردة
play is foundational for bonding relationships
ان اللعب هو وسيلة تواصل وتقوية للعلاقات
and fostering tolerance.
وهو وسيلة لنشر التراحم والتسامح فيما بيننا
It's where we learn to trust
وهو وسيلة لتوطيد الثقة
and where we learn about the rules of the game.
وهو الوسيلة التي تعلمنا " قواعد " الحياة
Play increases creativity
ان اللعب ينمي الابداع
and resilience,
ويساهم في استيعاب الحياة واكتساب المرونة مع صعابها
and it's all about the generation of diversity --
ان اللعب هو التمايز ..
diversity of interactions,
هو التنوع في ردات الفعل
diversity of behaviors,
التنوع في التصرفات والسلوك
diversity of connections.
التنوع في طرق التواصل
And when you watch bonobo play,
عندما تشاهد قردة البابون وهي تلعب ..
you're seeing the very evolutionary roots
سوف تلحظ الكثير من جذور التطور المتشابهة
of human laughter, dance
بين ضحك الانسان ... ورقصه
and ritual.
وطقوسه
Play is the glue
ان اللعب هو الرابط
that binds us together.
الذي يجمعنا سويةً
Now, I don't know how you play,
انا لا أعرف كيف تمارسون اللعب ..
but I want to show you a couple of unique clips
ولكن اريد ان اعرض عليكم مشهدين مميزين
fresh from the wild.
حديثين من البرية
First, it's a ball game bonobo-style --
الاول يظهر لنا " قردة البابون " وهي تمارس لعبة "الكرات"
and I do not mean football.
وانا لا اعني كرة القدم !
So here,
هنا نرى
we have a young female and a male
انثى يافعة .. وشاب يافع
engaged in a chase game.
يلاحقون بعضهم البعض
Have a look what she's doing.
انظروا مالذي تقوم به
It might be the evolutionary origin of the phrase,
ربما قد يكون هذا المشهد هو اساس العبارة
"she's got him by the balls."
" لقد نالت منه بضربها " خصيتيه " "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Only I think that he's rather loving it here, right?
واتصور ان الذكر مستمتع بهذا .. أليس كذلك
Yeah.
نعم !
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So sex play is common
ان الالعاب الجنسية .. شائعة
in both bonobos and humans.
سواء في فصيل " قردة البابون " .. او البشر
And this video is really interesting
وهذا المشهد مثير للاهتمام حقاً
because it shows --
لانه يظهر
this video's really interesting
قلت ان هذا المشهد مثير
because it shows the inventiveness
لانه يظهر مبادرة
of bringing unusual elements into play --
استخدام العناصر الاساسية المتوفرة كوسائل لللعب
such as testicles --
ك " الخصيتين " مثلاً
and also how play both requires trust
وكيف ان اللعب يتطلب الثقة من الطرفين
and fosters trust --
ثقة عمياء ..
while at the same time being tremendous fun.
حيث يولد اللعب متعة لا مثيل لها
But play's a shapeshifter.
ان اللعب وسيلة تغيير
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Play's a shapeshifter,
ان اللعب وسيلة تغيير ..
and it can take many forms,
يمكنها ان تأخذ عدة صور
some of which are more quiet,
بعضها ..قد يكون هادىء
imaginative, curious --
بعضها خيالي .. فضولي
maybe where wonder is discovered anew.
والكثير منها ينقلنا الى عالم العجائب
And I want you to see,
اريد منكم ان تشاهدوا
this is Fuku, a young female,
"فوكو" انها انثى يافعة
and she is quietly playing with water.
انها تلعب بواسطة الماء
I think, like her,
اعتقد .. كما هي تعتقد
we sometimes play alone,
ان اللعب الفردي
and we explore the boundaries
عادة ما يوسع من نطاقنا
of our inner and our outer worlds.
ويجعل التواصل مع عالمنا الداخلي والخارجي ممكنا
And it's that playful curiosity
ان هذا اللعب الفضولي
that drives us to explore, drives us to interact,
هو ما يدفعنا لاكتشاف المحيط .. ويدفعنا الى التواصل ..
and then the unexpected connections we form
ان هذه الاتصالات الغير متوقعة التي يُشكلها اللعب
are the real hotbed for creativity.
هي الاساس المحوري للابداع
So these are just small tasters
وهذه الامور هي التي يرينا
into the insights that bonobo give us
إياها مجتمع " قردة البابون "
to our past and present.
وهي صحيحة سواء في الماضي او في الحاضر
But they also hold a secret for our future,
وهي تحمل سر المستقبل ايضاً
a future where we need to adapt
المستقبل الذي يجب ان نتكيف معه
to an increasingly challenging world
ومع تحديات هذا العالم المتزايدة
through greater creativity
والتي لا يمكن لنا مواجهتها الا عن طريق الابداع
and greater cooperation.
والتعاون التام
The secret is that play is the key
والسر .. هو ان اللعب هذا .. هو
to these capacities.
المفتاح لكل هذه الامكانيات
In other words,
بصورة اخرى .
play is our adaptive wildcard.
ان اللعب هو ورقة التطور الرابحة
In order to adapt successfully
التي نملكها اليوم
to a changing world,
لكي نغير العالم
we need to play.
نحن نحتاج اليوم لللعب
But will we make the most of our playfulness?
هل سيجعلنا اللعب سخيفين ؟
Play is not frivolous.
ان اللعب ليس شيء تافه !
Play's essential.
انه محوري
For bonobos and humans alike,
سواء كان ذلك ل" قردة البابون " أو للبشر
life is not just red in tooth and claw.
ان الحياة ليست مجرد " جدية مطلقة "
In times when it seems least appropriate to play,
ففي الوقت الذي نظن انه الوقت الغير ملائم لللعب على الاطلاق
it might be the times when it is most urgent.
ربما يكون فيه اللعب ضرورياً جداً
And so, my fellow primates,
لذا .. يا أقربائي ..
let us embrace this gift from evolution
دعونا نقدس هدية " سلم التطور " لنا
and play together,
و نلعب سويةً
as we rediscover creativity,
ونعيد اكتشاف الابداع
fellowship and wonder.
والتواصل . .. والعجائب
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)